An official meeting took place
政府召開正式會議
two days after the appearance of the orifices.
是在洞出現的兩天後
The ministers who attended the meeting were perplexed,
所有與會者都面面相覷
and the discussion began with what should be addressed first at the meeting.
首先商量的是整件事該從何談起
I wonder who dug those orifices.
究竟是誰挖的？
Oh, come on.
這問題可想而知 哪有人能在空中挖洞啊
What should we do about them?
該怎麼處理那些洞呢？
And whose jurisdiction do they fall under?
說到底該歸誰管？
That must be under your jurisdiction, the Ministry of Defense.
當然是你們防衛省要出面吧
It's not like we're under attack. Shouldn't it be yours?
那又不是什麼武力攻擊 是你們的責任才對吧？
No.
不，我從沒聽說過 空中會自行開出大洞
Since they are floating in the air, shouldn't they be considered culture?
不如說洞浮在空中，算是一種藝術吧
Is that so?
是嗎？
Yes, they're art, so you should place them under your jurisdiction.
那確實是藝術 應當由你們單位處置吧
That is a good idea.
我認為是個好主意
Is it?
真是如此嗎？
Exactly. It's 100,000 yen per person for investigating the orifices.
對，我方會提供 每人十萬圓的經費調查那些洞
It shouldn't be too hard. What do you think?
不是件難事吧，能替我辦嗎？
I'm sure we will find participants in no time.
當然馬上就能辦好，我會找到人手的
Could you find people who are willing to investigate for 30,000 yen?
沒錯，我會提供每人三萬圓 希望你能幫忙找人來調查大洞
It won't be anything difficult or dangerous.
這件事不難辦，調查工作也不危險
Yes, of course.
好，我知道了
The government says it's not dangerous, so it should be fine.
政府說沒有危險性 我想不會有問題的
As for remuneration,
至於調查大洞的酬勞
each participant will get 15,000 yen for investigating the orifices.
我們預計給每人一萬五千圓
Leave it to me. I'll handle it.
包在我身上，請放心交給我們辦
We're the only ones you've asked, right?
順便想確認 你們沒有再找其他廠商談吧？
Can you find some young people who are willing to work for 5,000 yen?
召集年輕人，給他們每人五千圓吧
Until recently, I was working at a music box museum.
我直到最近都在音樂盒紀念館打工
What's that?
什麼是音樂盒紀念館？
It's like an art museum run by the town
簡單來說 就是類似鎮上美術館的地方
but it specializes in music boxes.
只是展覽的主題是音樂盒
There might not be one around here.
在這一帶可能沒有
The part-timers who were trying to fill up the orifices eventually entered them.
做埋洞打工的人最終也被列在其中啊
Where do you live now?
你現在住哪裡？
I live here now but I used to live in the countryside.
我目前住這座城市，之前住在鄉下
A lot of people moved here since the orifices appeared.
因為有洞出現 所以搬來這裡的人變多了呢
I didn't move here because of that.
那不是我過來的主因
-Oh. -Well…
-哦 -那個…
I've been moving around a lot.
我本來就經常搬家
I thought it would be nice to live in a peaceful place,
因為我想住在安穩的地方
so I was looking around.
於是到處找適合的住所
Because of that, I didn't have a fixed job, to be honest.
老實說我也沒有固定的工作
Amidst all the moving around,
而是不停在轉職
I had come to live here once before.
我之前也來過這座城市
Let me tell you in chronological order.
按照順序來說的話
I used to work at a library.
我一開始在圖書館任職
It wasn't being used much and it closed down
那間圖書館沒什麼人會去
because they couldn't afford to keep it open for the few patrons.
沒辦法只為少數人繼續花錢經營 因此便倒閉了
After that, I wanted to be bold
接著我就打算果斷一些
and moved here to get a completely different job.
直接換個工作性質，於是前來此地
I'm going to pick up the bento boxes!
我去拿便當！
Matsuoka got a job at an advertising agency.
松岡改到一家廣告製作公司上班
At first, I was enthusiastic,
起初我還想全力以赴地努力
but the work schedule was really brutal.
然而工作行程卻是滿檔狀態
It was so different from the library.
和在圖書館那時相比 簡直是天差地別
I hardly had time to sleep, my motivation declined,
我幾乎沒時間好好睡覺 長久以來情緒越來越低落
and I was exhausted.
體力也逐漸耗盡
I'm sure this company would have hired anyone.
讓我不禁認為 任誰來這家公司都會被錄取
No one worked here for long.
大家都做不久，馬上就辭職
I mean, who would want to work for such an exploitative company?
要是知道這是間血汗公司 根本就沒人會想進來吧？
Talented people would definitely get a different job.
越是優秀的人越會去找其他工作
I said that's too much light. It's way too bright.
就跟你說燈光太強了，這樣太亮了
And I'm telling you it won't be visible.
不這麼亮看不清楚啊
-Of course it's visible! -No, it's not!
-看得見啦，很清楚！ -哪有，看不清楚啦！
Are you for real?
你是不是腦子壞啦？
Do it yourself, then.
不然你自己弄啊
I thought about stopping them.
我有想過要勸架
But they were big names in the industry and I was a newbie.
不過對方是資深的前輩 而我只是個新人
Besides, I didn't want to deal with angry adult men.
何況會大聲吼罵的男人 我本來就應付不來
Yet, I had to tell them the bento boxes were here
但如果不告訴他們便當來了
or a superior would yell at me.
事後我會被上頭責罵
You can't handle it alone, can you?
難道你一個人搞得定嗎？
That's not the point.
重點不在這裡吧
Do you have a problem with me?
既然有意見你就自己來啊
I'm just telling you it's too bright, so turn down the light a notch.
就跟你說燈光太亮 調暗一點就行了啊
What part of this is too bright?
到底是哪裡太亮啦？
Um…
不好意思
The bento boxes are here.
便當來了
They are over there.
便當來了，就在那裡
Are you okay? What's wrong?
你還好嗎？怎麼了？
If I don't announce the bento boxes, I'll get scolded.
如果不告訴你們便當來了，我會被罵
Right.
我想也是啦
Did you get yelled at?
有人罵你嗎？
We weren't fighting or anything.
我們不是在吵架喔
It's just our usual playful banter.
這只是我們平常順勢會開的玩笑而已
I-It's too much.
太難看出來了
How should I have known?
我怎麼會知道啊？
He tends to use too much light, so we were just messing around.
我們時常會針對燈光太亮鬥嘴 是平時會開的玩笑，讓你誤會了啊
You were yelling.
因為你們在大吼啊
We weren't fighting, though.
不過我們沒有吵架
But I thought it was too bright too.
可是我也覺得太亮了
You mean me?
是在說我？
The lighting.
燈光
My lighting?
我的燈光？
I was wondering if it might be too bright.
亮到讓我很擔心
Was it too much?
奇怪，有那麼亮嗎？
It was so bright, I thought about suggesting
因為實在太亮了，我本來也想問你們
to turn down the light a bit.
是不是調暗一點比較好
You?
你是這麼想的啊？
I thought if the filming crew was okay with it…
但我又覺得攝影組能接受就好
But the light…
只是照出來的燈光…
The light was…
燈光的亮度…
It was as if the light was burning the subject to death.
看起來亮到會燒死人
Was it that bad? Don't you think that's a bit extreme?
有那麼誇張嗎？不至於吧？
You were using that much light.
可是在我看來就是那麼亮
I thought the actor might catch fire.
我很怕藝人的身體會燒起來
Oh, but…
哦，這樣啊，不過真的是滿亮的啦
Sorry.
抱歉
It's okay.
我不介意
Matsuoka decided to quit her job.
松岡決定辭職
Who was I doing all this for?
我不禁想著“我在做什麼？ 做這些到底都是為了誰？”
I couldn't keep going anymore and wanted to go someplace quiet.
已經無法再努力下去了
Then, why did you start working at the music box museum right away?
即使是那樣，為何馬上就去 音樂盒紀念館工作？
Because I needed to make a living.
因為不工作就會餓死啊
It might have been better if I had taken some time off.
或許休息一陣子會比較好
The strange thing is…
不過說來神奇
When you're in a state where you can't take a break,
人處於無法休息的狀態時
the option of taking a break is not even on the table.
腦中自然就不會浮現“休息”的選項
Have you moved out of that house?
你已經搬離原本的住處了嗎？
Yes, I'm already living here.
是的，我搬來這裡了
Our museum is…
其實我們的紀念館啊…
How should I put it…
該怎麼說呢？
We only get very few visitors.
只會有少數人進來參觀
It might be a boring place to work at for someone your age.
以你的年紀來看 可能會覺得這份工作很無趣
That's okay.
沒關係
Even on busy days, we only get about five visitors.
一天頂多只會有五個人來訪
During the offseason, it's even less.
在觀光客較少的淡季人會更少
There are plenty of other places that offer better pay.
打工時薪比這裡高的地方比比皆是
I'm good at finding something to do.
我很擅長自己找事做
If a group comes, please guide them along the route I just showed you.
假如有團體客來訪 請你引導他們走這條路線
Although groups only come once a year tops.
雖然依實際情況來看 一年都不見得能遇上一次
Just be prepared to guide them in case they do come.
不過還是請你先熟悉 以便有人來時能夠應對
Noted.
我記住了
And… that's the stage.
然後那是舞台
You do plays?
平常會有表演嗎？
Only when we have reservations,
當客人事先預約時
we reach out to the city's theater group and they perform fairy tales.
我們會邀請在市內活動的劇團
Mostly, it's part of a school's extracurricular activity.
大多都只有學校 舉辦戶外教學時才會有演出
One day, when Matsuoka was working her shift.
事情發生在她某天打工的時候
There were a total of six visitors on that day.
這天一共有六位訪客
We're with the theater group.
我們是來表演的劇團
-I'll show you-- -It's okay. We know where to go.
-我來幫忙帶路… -沒關係，我們知道在哪
Oh, go on in.
好吧，請進
Among the six visitors that day,
這天的六位訪客之中
one had reserved a seat for the performance.
有其中一位預訂了舞台劇的票
Although Matsuoka had only been working here for a few weeks,
雖然松岡才剛來工作幾週
this was the first reservation and she found it unusual.
但也是第一次碰上有人預約 因此她覺得很稀奇
Excuse me.
不好意思，我有預訂舞台劇的票 我叫原幸惠
Thank you for coming.
恭候多時了
Who is it?
-是哪位啊？ -是我，小紅帽
Oh, Little Red Riding Hood. Come on in.
是小紅帽啊，快進來吧
I'm not feeling well and can't get out of bed.
我身體不太舒服，沒辦法走下床
Hello, Grandmother.
你好，奶奶
Your ears are so big, Grandmother.
奶奶，你的耳朵好大喔
Yes, so I can hear better what you say.
是啊，這是為了聽清楚你的聲音
And your eyes are large and shiny.
而且你的眼睛好大，還會發光
It's a little scary.
看起來好可怕喔
No need to be scared.
不用害怕
It's so I can see you better, my dear.
這是為了看清楚你可愛的模樣啊
Your hands are quite large too, Grandmother.
再加上奶奶的手也好大喔
Have they always been this large?
奶奶的手原本就這麼大嗎？
No need to be afraid.
不用害怕
If I didn't have large hands, I wouldn't be able to hold you in my arms.
要是手沒這麼大
On a different day.
又到了某一天
Matsuoka came to work
松岡來打工之後
to find the name "Yukie Hara" on the reservation list.
在預約名冊上發現了 “原幸惠”這名字
It hadn't even been a week
那天距離她上次看戲
since she had attended the previous performance.
還不到一星期的時間
Excuse me.
不好意思
I reserved tickets for today's show. I'm Yukie Hara.
我有預訂舞台劇的票，我叫原幸惠
To be honest, I found the show was even more boring than commercials.
老實說看了舞台劇後 我覺得比廣告還無聊
For a minute, I wondered if
一時還不禁懷疑
there was nothing better to do here than watch the same show twice.
這個地區究竟有多荒涼 會讓人想來這裡看兩次戲
But then, I realized it was a coincidence that they had the same name.
而且偏偏是同名同姓的人 對這種巧合我感到意外
Hello, Grandmother.
你好，奶奶
Have your ears always been so big, Grandmother?
奶奶，你的耳朵原本就這麼大嗎？
Matsuoka was curious about
-松岡很好奇這位原幸惠… -是啊，這是為了聽清楚
how this Yukie Hara would watch the show.
-你的聲音 -會以什麼方式看舞台劇
Therefore, she watched her from behind.
-便從後方觀察她的樣子 -而且你的眼睛好大，還會發光
As did the other Yukie Hara,
-而兩位原幸惠… -看起來好可怕喔
she, too, was simply staring at the stage.
-同樣都只是靜靜地看著舞台 -不用害怕，這是為了看清楚
Your hands are quite large too, Grandmother.
再加上奶奶的手也好大喔
I've been living here for a while but I didn't know there was a place like this.
我一直住在這附近 不過之前都不曉得還有這樣的地方
Have you seen the museum as well?
你逛過其他展區了嗎？
Yes, I did. Although there's not much to see.
我逛了一圈，好冷清喔
It's nice and calm, though.
雖然能讓人平心靜氣，也不錯啦
Do you happen to know someone by the same name
請問你認不認識住這附近 一位跟你同名的住戶？
She's around the same age as you.
她的年紀跟你差不多
No, I don't.
我不認識耶
A little while ago,
前幾天有一位跟你同名同姓的女生
When I saw the reservation list today,
所以今天看到預約名冊時
I thought she had come to watch it a second time.
我以為她要來看第二次
Oh, really?
這樣啊
Does she come here often?
那個人很常來嗎？
I've only started working here recently,
我才剛來上班沒多久
so I'm not sure about that.
所以不太清楚
Maybe I should come here from time to time.
那我偶爾有空時會再來逛逛
Ms. Hara really started coming here regularly.
實際上幸惠小姐之後又來了好幾次
She didn't get to meet the other Yukie Hara.
但始終沒遇上第一位原幸惠小姐
Instead, she ended up frequently engaging in conversation with me.
反倒是和我聊天逐漸成了她的習慣
For the past six months,
這半年以來
you've been the only person who's been watching the play.
來看舞台劇的人都只有你一位
It's hard to cross paths.
一直沒能見上一面呢
Matsuoka tried to figure out
松岡開始思考是否能夠設法
Recalling her fading memories of the other Yukie Hara,
於是松岡便一邊回想 快記不清長相的另一位原幸惠的臉
Matsuoka started searching the internet.
一邊在網上搜尋
That's it.
就是這樣
Now, tap here to upload your picture.
然後點一下這裡，再上傳自己的照片
Does it have to be a picture of myself?
一定要放自己的照片嗎？
It can be anything, like a landscape for example.
也可以放風景照或是其他喜歡的照片
Then, I'll use a photo of my dog.
那就放我家小狗的照片吧
Now, type "Yukie Hara" into this search bar.
接著在搜尋欄輸入
There are a lot of them.
跳出好多搜尋結果喔
This is the other Yukie Hara.
這個人就是原幸惠小姐
Well, they're all called Yukie Hara but…
不過這些人都叫原幸惠就是了
If you tap here, you can send a message.
再點一下這裡，就能傳訊息了
I see.
原來如此
Maybe I should use a photo of myself instead of my dog.
不然我也換成自己的頭像吧
Could you take a photo of me?
可以幫我拍一張嗎？
Sure.
當然可以
Okay.
好
-Are you ready? -Yes.
-我要拍囉 -好
What do you think?
你看看如何
The lighting is perfect.
光線很漂亮呢
Let's take one at the museum next time.
下次也在紀念館拍張照吧
What should I write?
該傳什麼訊息才好呢？
Is it okay to message her out of the blue?
話說真的可以突然傳給對方嗎？
Yes, of course.
可以喔
"Hello, I'm Yukie Hara."
“你好，我是原幸惠”
I bet she'll be surprised when she reads this.
這麼寫會害對方嚇一跳吧
The two Yukie Haras connected through social media.
於是兩位原幸惠 透過社群平台聯絡上彼此
It turned out that the other Yukie Hara was
她們得知第一位幸惠
in the arts business and was working in Germany.
在德國從事藝術相關的工作
Therefore, she currently wasn't in Japan.
目前人不在日本
However, they promised to meet up
不過她承諾回到日本時
the next time she returned to Japan.
一定會找機會跟她見面
Six years have passed since then.
後來經過六年
I quit my job at the music box museum.
我辭去了音樂盒紀念館的工作
Now I work at this small public bathhouse.
目前在這家小澡堂上班
It's modern and provides a comfortable working environment.
這裡的澡堂很先進 有非常良好的工作環境
"Ms. Matsuoka, I hope you are doing well."
“松岡小姐，好久不見
"I have news."
我聯絡你是想告訴你一件事
"I have kept in touch with Yukie Hara and I am going to meet her."
我和持續有在聯繫的 原幸惠小姐約好要見面
"It's been six years."
經過了六年的歲月
"She is finally coming back from Germany."
她終於要從德國回來了
"It's all thanks to you, Ms. Matsuoka."
多虧有你，我才能聯絡上對方
"Would you like to join us?"
要是方便 你要不要也一同赴約呢？”
It's nice to see you again.
好久不見
Who is it?
-是哪位啊？ -是我，小紅帽
Oh, Little Red Riding Hood. Come on in.
是小紅帽啊，快進來吧
I'm not feeling well and can't get out of bed.
我身體不太舒服，沒辦法走下床
Hello, Grandmother.
你好，奶奶
Your ears are so big, Grandmother.
奶奶，你的耳朵好大喔
Yes, so I can hear better what you say.
是啊，這是為了聽清楚你的聲音
And your eyes are large and shiny.
而且你的眼睛好大，還會發光
It's a little scary.
看起來好可怕喔
No need to be scared.
不用害怕
It's so I can see you better, my dear.
這是為了看清楚你可愛的模樣啊
Your hands are quite large too, Grandmother.
再加上奶奶的手也好大喔
Have they always been this large?
奶奶的手原本就這麼大嗎？
No need to be afraid.
不用害怕
If I didn't have large hands, I wouldn't be able to hold you in my arms.
要是手沒這麼大
Your mouth is very large too.
然後奶奶的嘴巴也好大
Has it always been so large?
奶奶的嘴巴原本就這麼大嗎？
Even after six years, it was still boring.
過了六年再來看，果然還是一樣無聊
Yet the two of them simply stared at the stage.
-即使如此… -會怎麼樣？
The two Yukie Haras had found
兩位原幸惠小姐
many similarities between each other.
彼此找到了許多共通點
Not only did they have the same name,
不只姓名完全相同
but they were the same age and shared the same birthday.
居然就連年齡也一樣 生日也在同一天
Even their dogs had the same birthday and were the same breed.
甚至連寵物狗的生日
However, they were born and raised in different places.
只有她們生長的地方完全不同
The other Yukie Hara had visited this place just by chance.
據說原幸惠小姐 當初只是碰巧來此觀光而已
Let's meet up here again next time I come back from Germany.
下次我從德國回來 我們再約在這裡見面吧
Yes, let's. I need to stay healthy until then.
好啊，不知道會是何時的事 我得健健康康的才行
Although that play is boring.
那場舞台劇好無趣
Will they still be performing it?
不曉得會不會一直演下去
They've been doing it for six years, so I'm sure they'll keep it boring.
六年來都演得一樣無聊 到時候肯定還會繼續演的
You should come too, Ms. Matsuoka.
松岡小姐也要來喔
Next time, let's have dinner together.
下次也一起吃晚餐吧
Yes.
好
Seeing them made me wish to age gracefully as well.
因此我就期許自己 也能像她們那樣老去
That's why I came back to this town.
最終又回到了這座城市
But…
只不過呢
Two years ago, I was diagnosed with an illness.
前年我得知自己生了病
So…
我的年齡確實有增長
Well…
然而就算不期望
She's not coming back from Germany for four years?
她下一次從德國回來 預計是在四年後啊？
What does she do for work?
她在從事什麼樣的工作？
Something related to the arts.
這個嘛，好像是藝術類的
I'm not very familiar with the kind of work she does.
並不是很常見的工作
I see.
這樣啊
But the orifices are there for us.
但是我們有洞
Maybe you can meet her in there.
你或許能在洞的另一邊與她相見
Do they have orifices in Germany too?
德國也有這種洞嗎？
In Germany…
在德國沒有耶
Not in Germany.
德國沒有洞
Oh, okay.
是喔，沒有啊
So, if she wants to enter one,
所以若是想走進洞裡
she'll need to come back to Japan.
她就必須回到日本
We don't know if she wants to enter, though.
但我們也不知道她想不想進洞
She might not enter.
有可能不會進去
But even if she doesn't enter…
不過即使如此…
We will meet inside the orifices one day.
我們總有一天都能在洞的另一邊相會
I assure you.
絕對會的
Are you allowed to drink alcohol?
你喝酒了耶，不要緊嗎？
That's a good question.
我也不確定耶
Shoot.
糟糕，肉烤焦了
-I'll eat this, then. -Really?
那我就吃這個吧
Burned food is bad for you.
烤焦的食物對身體不好喔
I don't want to let it go to waste.
可是不吃就太浪費啦
I'll take this one.
我開動了
-Can I use those chopsticks? -Go ahead.
-我可以拿雙筷子嗎？ -請便
Thank you.
-謝謝 -不客氣
Hey, Mom.
喂？媽媽
I've decided to enter the orifices today.
我今天要進洞裡了
Yeah, today.
對，就是今天
Okay.
好
Thanks, I'll be careful.
謝謝，我會小心的
Yeah, thanks.
謝謝你
Do you think there's reception in the orifices?
不知道洞裡收不收得到訊號
I'm not sure.
連得上嗎？
It might be bad, right?
不過照理來說，訊號應該不太好
Subtitle translation by: Mariko Yasuoka-Sator
字幕翻譯：劉莉茜
I'm thinking of letting her quit.
對，所以我考慮別讓她去了
I was born in the UK.
其實我是在英國出生的
She still can only speak English and can't fit in at school.
她目前還只會講英文 在學校格格不入
So she wants to do ballet?
她說很想學芭蕾？
I didn't choose to be born in this body.
又不是我自願以這副身體誕生的
It's not my fault.
不能交談不是我的錯
Objectively?
從客觀的角度來說嗎？
Maybe someone who wants to go pro should go.
把機會讓給想成為 專業人士的人比較好吧
It's all about talent.
這關係到天賦吧
Dramaism.
Dramaism
Seven Orifices. Episode 4.
《驚天七洞》，第4集